<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The state of blessedness by W.W.</title>
            <author>W. W., M.A. and chaplain to a person of honour.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65568</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W153</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26302</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09418383</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09418383</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43037</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65568)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43037)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1319:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The state of blessedness by W.W.</title>
                  <author>W. W., M.A. and chaplain to a person of honour.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published at the request of a person of quality."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Colossians I, 12 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Heaven --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43037:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43037:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE STATE OF BLESSEDNESS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. W.</hi> M. A. and Chaplain, to a Perſon of Honour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed at the requeſt of a Perſon of Quality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Bible and Three Crowns in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mercers Chappel,</hi> and at the Bible on <hi>London Bridge</hi> under the Gate, 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:43037:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43037:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFUL <hi>Sir</hi> John Roberts <hi>BARONETT.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HEre is your Requeſt; and I wiſh that you do not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent you of it: That you do not diſcover greater failings by deliberate Reading, then you did in the tranſient Hearing of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. It hath received ſome en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement and alteration ſince I Preach'd it, and not without need; for the Truth is, the Subject was too great for me, and handled in too much haſt: The Sermon being the immature conception of thoſe few
<pb facs="tcp:43037:3"/>hours, which that weeks exerciſe afforded me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I am much afraid it will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver anſwer that eſteem you was pleaſed to expreſs for it, but if it may be (in any degree) ſerviceable to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward your attainment of the Glory it treats of, I ſhall be abundantly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured and recompenſed, for thus expoſing my ſelf. The hopes whereof is the greateſt motive and encouragement to this bold attempt of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt obliged Servant, <hi>W. W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43037:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>COLOSSIANS</hi> 1.12.</bibl>
               <q>—The Saints in Light.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>NOT to trouble you with more then barely my Thoughts upon this expreſſion, we ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Saints in a double capacity.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As they are the ſincere members of the Militant Church here on Earth. And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. As they are the glorified members of the Church Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant in Heaven.</p>
            <p>The Light in which the Saints Militant dwell, and by which they ſteer and direct their lives, is the Goſpel of our Saviour, whereof Light is a proper Character; for it's plainneſs and perſpicuity in all things neceſſary to be known: For the diſcoveries it hath made of Life and immortality, which were either hidden from foregoing ages, or but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely and myſtically revealed; for unvailing <hi>Moſes</hi>'s face, both explaining the deſigned difficulties of the Law, and unfolding it from thoſe thicker ſhrouds of darkneſs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in humane Tradition, and the falſe gloſſes of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> had enwrapt it. For opening to us a proſpect and inſight into ſome parts and perfections of Religion and Vertue, which Nature and the Law were ignorant of: For delivering the Hiſtory of the Son of God, who is that true Eſſential Light which lighteth every man that cometh into the World. And laſtly, For the concurrence ſake of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43037:4"/>Holy Spirit, which always attends the Goſpel to enlighten and direct the underſtandings, of thoſe that by a modeſt and conſcientious diligence and enquiry, ſearch and labour after ſaving knowledge.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, The Saints conſidered in a higher capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, Triumphant with God in Heaven, I purpoſe for my preſent Theme, as I ſuppoſe them to have been deſign'd by the Apoſtle in the Words before us. Whereupon I ſhall not attempt to Landskip Heaven, or deſcribe that inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſible light which neither eye hath ſeen, nor the thoughts of man conceiv'd; but only ſum up to you what God hath reveal'd, what the underſtanding of man is able to think of it, and what concluſions we may reaſonably ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of our future happineſs, by reflecting upon our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent wants: Still keeping within the bounds of the Text, and the metaphorical importance of the expreſſion, and as 'tis counterpoſed to that figurative darkneſs which in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we ſo often read of.</p>
            <p>Light then (as 'tis uſed for that State of Bleſſedneſs which the Saints enjoy) is a term of infinite comprehenſion, and concludes in it all the good, all the joy, all the perfection that go to the making up of Heaven. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sight is the moſt delicate and pleaſurable of the ſences, as <hi>Solomon</hi> teſtifies, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.30. <hi>The Light of the Eyes rejoyceth the Heart:</hi> And ſo the ſame Author, <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 11.7. <hi>Truly the light is ſweet, and a pleaſant thing it is for the Eyes to behold the Sun.</hi> That to deſcribe Heaven by Viſion, intimates it to be a ſtate of exquiſite delights, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; and thoſe pleaſures (like light) are pure and refined; and ſuch undoubtedly they are, being purged from the groſs mixtures of luſt and ſenſuality, and adapted to the chaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of ſanctified Spirits, and the Holy appetites of unvitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Reaſon. They are quite of another nature, then thoſe fordid and unmanly pleaſures, wherewith the carnal world entertain their degenerous inclinations; nay they are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted from thoſe defects and imperfections, drawn off from thoſe dregs, that (in this life) taint and imbitter the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ational delights of the wiſeſt and beſt of men. They
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43037:4"/>are under no reſtraints of ſize and meaſure, but infinitely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound; they are not checkt by the fears of exceſs in the enjoyment, for they are as innocent as delightful: They are not ſuch luſcious ſweets as ſatiate the appetites of thoſe that taſt them, but at the fame time both fulfil their deſires, and enlarge them; theſe are ingenuous and heroick plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, conſiſting in the perfection of Wiſedom, and Love, and Holineſs, thoſe charms and graces of glorified ſouls, in the viſion and inſeperable enjoyment of God, their cheif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt deſirable object, in the acquaintance and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the glorious company of the Apoſtles, the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſociety of the Prophets, the noble Army of Martyrs, and of all the braveſt Worthies of the World. Oh! What an eternal rapture of Joy muſt it needs prove for theſe Bleſſed Souls. Theſe deareſt Friends, to meet in the ſame place, to be concentred in the ſame happineſs, to be link'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in mutual affections and embraces, never to know ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row nor diſcord, nor parting again. Theſe are harmleſs but moſt charming pleaſures; pleaſures fit to entertain great and generous minds, that favour not of Earth and ſenſuality: Pleaſures that unconceivably delight and raviſh, but leave neither guilt nor ſting behind them: Pleaſures ſo conſtant and ſucceſſive that they ſhall leave no room for a moments unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to interpoſe; and ſo endleſs and immortal, that they ſhall never expire, nor give place to a worſe ſucceſſion. Such vaſt advantages have they of thoſe foulſome and nauſeous Luſts, which carnal Dotards rate above their ſouls, and for which they barter them, that it is their great perfection to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like them; For the joy of Heaven, the felicity of Saints, is without meaſure, without allay, without ſin, without intermiſſion, and without end. Even the innocent Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of good men, are (in this World) ſubject to be baw'kt and daunted, and the great care and pains where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are firſt obtained and then ſecur'd, is a mighty abatement to them; but it is not the leaſt happineſs of Saints, that when they dye in the Lord, they reſt from their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. Thoſe ſick and ſhort lived joys that the world affords, are ſo inconſiderable, that the coſt and travail of acquiring
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43037:5"/>them, generally exceed the purchaſe: But thoſe that the Saints enjoy are as cheap as day-light, and come freely in without their ſeeking: all pains and forecaſts are there ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſeded, by the fatisfactory proviſions that God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, and the repoſed contentment of their own minds. They have no hungry, importunate appetites to care and purvey for, they have no ſhameful nakedneſs to cloath, and cover; they are many degrees above the ſcorchings of the Sun by day, and the pale and chilly influences of the Moon by Night; and therefore they need not be at the trouble to raiſe Fortifications againſt extremity of Weather, to erect Booths and plant gourds to ſhelter from the heat, nor to Build, Repair and Alter, to guard the tender ſences from the injurious Elements,—<hi>quibus ſollicitis fervet Respublica curis,</hi> for at this rate the world purchaſe and enſure their Health, and Eaſe, and Pleaſure: But the Bleſſed are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to thoſe calm and pleaſant Regions, where none of thoſe Storms and Troubles, none of thoſe ſtraights and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, none of thoſe changes and uncertainties, which diſcompoſe this lower world, (and ſo buſie the hands and thoughts of men, to prevent or remove them) can make their approaches, but they inhabit thoſe manſions of eternal reſt, that are exempted from all diſturbance and uneaſineſs; and even the very fears of any, where Fortune and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy have nought to do: And what need can there be of their labour or thoughtfulneſs, when there is nothing want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which they have not, neither any waſt or decay of what they have; but all things they enjoy are (like the houſe in which they dwell) made to their hands, nay made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hands, eternal in the Heavens?</p>
            <p>And then for thoſe ſpiritual joys which the Righteous, in this Life, Taſt (and yet they do but taſt them) how hardly do they come by them! What an hoſt of difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties muſt they break through e're they can attain them? They muſt abjure the pleaſures of the World, ſacrifice their moſt endeared intereſts, ſtem the current of nature, deny the cravings of ſence and inclination, repent and mourn, Watch and Pray, conquer Sin and Devils, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43037:5"/>and ſtrictly tie themſelves up to the rigorous obſervance of all the Laws of God (that are ſo irkſome to fleſh and blood) before they can tell what Peace of Conſcience or Joy in the Holy Ghoſt mean. For thoſe Raptures and Tranſports, thoſe ſudden flaſhes of Light and Joy, which ſometimes poſſeſs the minds of bad men, who never paid ſo dear for them, are but counterfeit and Enthuſiaſtick: But the joyes of Heaven tide themſelves into the ſouls of the Bleſſed, without their trouble and pains to dig a current for them: There's nothing lies in the way betwixt them and their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs that may either hinder their enjoyment, or be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome to remove: They have no ſins to repent of, no headſtrong Wills to break and ſubdue, no wild unruly Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to tame, no evils, no Temptations to Watch and Pray againſt, <hi>ne voto opus erit,</hi> all the difficulties of Religion are there made void and abrogated: God abates them all the duties they owe to him, but the chearful ſervices of Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving and Praiſe, and takes them off from all they owe to Men (making void Relations, and ſetting Kings and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, Fathers and Children, Maſters and Servants, the Rich and Poor, the Aged and the Infant, upon the ſame level) except the endearing and grateful duties of Love and Union. Thus the Saints enjoy their Pleaſures in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect eaſe and reſt, and have nothing at all to do (either for Souls or Bodies) but to be happy.</p>
            <p>But there's one Thought more in the notion of reſt which ſhould not be omitted, becauſe it ſo raiſes and enlivens the pleaſure of Saints, and gives them an advantage of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs above Angels themſelves. Reſt preſuppoſes labour, labour that's paſt and over; and how will the ſence and memory of what they did and endur'd, add to the bliſſe they now enjoy! What a new Heaven will it be to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the World they went through, and the Hell they eſcap't! How will it enhance their Joy, to recount their troubles! How will it ſet off the ſtate of Glory to compare it with the miſeries of this ſinful World! Oh! How will they bleſs themſelves to reflect, by what narrow eſcapes,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43037:6"/>through what hardſhips and dangers, with what ſtruglings and conflicts, in what Agonies of deſpair and hope, in what a deluge of ſweat and tears, with what bitter cries and ſtrong deſires their poor ſouls at laſt arrived ſafe, into the Boſom of their reſt and refuge, never to return to know the like again!</p>
            <p n="2">2. Light and Dominion are ſometimes in Scripture pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly uſed for one another, thus ſaid Holy <hi>David</hi> in his laſt ſpeech, when the Spirit of the Lord was upon him, <hi>He that Ruleth over men, — Shall be as the Light of the Morning:</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3, 4. So when <hi>Jeroboam</hi> wreſted the ten Tribes out of the hands of <hi>Solomon,</hi> God thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed for <hi>Davids</hi> ſake, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto his Son will I give one Tribe that David my Servant may have a Light,</hi> (i. e. one to heir his Throne) <hi>always before me in Jeruſalem,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.36. And on the other hand the Pſalmiſt ſays, <hi>That God made great Lights, the Sun to Rule by Day, and the Moon to Rule by Night.</hi> And I am ſure the ſtate of the Bleſſed is a State of Dominion and Sovereignty, as well as Light, whether the expreſſion intend ſo much or no: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is called a Kingdom and a Crown of Glory, and the Saints are entitled Kings, and are ſaid to Reign with Chriſt. Kings they are in the Rule and Government of that mighty Empire of their own Minds; a Power greater then that of all the Kings of the Earth, who are not able to give Laws to any one ſoul.</p>
            <p>Now the Glory of a Kingdom is Peace, to be ſecure from all invaſions and encroachments from abroad, and from Rebellions and Mutinies at home; and this is the happy condition of Crowned Spirits. Devils may roar and envy to ſee their greatneſs and glory, which they cannot hinder nor deface, bad men may ſpight them, but they cannot hurt them: Thoſe damned Spirits, that plagued and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted them in the World, may vex and torment themſelves and broyl in the heat of their own diſappointed malice, but though they curſe and rage, the gates of Hell cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43037:6"/>There's no acceſs to any thing that's Evil; <hi>Lazarus</hi> is ſafe from <hi>Dives</hi>'s revenge: There's a great Gulf (the irreverſible decree of God) between them; and that which confirms the Miſery of the one, ſecures the peace and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the other.</p>
            <p>And then in Heaven, There's an univerſal peace through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Roval Neighbourhood, God is perfectly reconcil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to every one of them, and they to one another: They are all united in an infringible League of eternal Friendſhip and Alliance; and are ſo nearly concerned for each others VVelfare and Honour, and their intereſts ſo mingled and combin'd, that no one of them could be happy if any one of them ſhould not be ſo. That there's no fear of a breach among themſelves, whoſe mutual dependencies make them infallibly ſecure of one another.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Every ſoul is happy in the Government of it ſelf, and ſettles all its faculties in peace and order.</p>
            <p>Death ends the great controverſie between the Fleſh and Spirit, and thoſe affections that would ſometimes revolt and lean to the wrong ſide, ſhall be perfectly reduc'd and become faithful: There ſhall be no more bitter chidings between an enraged, injured Conſcience, and a Tyrannous arbitrary Will. The warm diſputes between Faith and Reaſon ſhall be ſtated and determin'd: The conflicts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Hope and Fear ſhall have an end, and all the jars and contradictions of our croſs and perverſe paſſions ſhall be laid aſide: Every faculty ſhall comply and yield to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Reaſon, and there ſhall be no diſſention, no Schiſm in the Soul; Oh! Happy is that State with which neither God nor man hath any quarrel, happy that Church where the Head and every Member are inſeperably joynted and ſinew'd together, by Unity and Concord; happy that Man that is reconciled to God, in Charity withal Men, and at Peace in his own Conſcience: If you can fancy any bliſs in theſe, (and I wiſh that our experience may teach us of this Nation to underſtand them all) then conceive
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43037:7"/>how incomparably happy the Saints are; and how deſirable a place the Kingdom of Heaven is, where bleſſed Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers are they all!</p>
            <p n="3">3. By Light we may underſtand Liberty, as it's oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite is taken for reſtraint, St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>Jude</hi> tell us that the laps'd Angels are impriſon'd in chains of Darkneſs till the day of Judgment, and the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> foretold that the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ſhould be for a Light to the Gentiles, to open the eyes of the blind, and to bring them that ſit in darkneſs, out of the Priſon houſe, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 42.6, 7. Where darkneſs and Priſon-houſe ſignifie the ſame thing, <hi>viz.</hi> A reſtraint of Mind, a narrowneſs of underſtanding: So we ſay of a Recluſe (a man of cloſe retirement) that he dwells in darkneſs, that he does not ſee the Light; as if he had not eye-room, not ſpace enough to look about him, but light is a ſpacious thing and of a vaſt extant and therefore a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Metaphor to expreſs Liberty by.</p>
            <p>Now the Liberty of Saints conſiſt in the Freedom of of Thought and Action, and enjoyment, a latitude to do and think their own pleaſure: Not that Heaven is a lawleſs place of Sin and diſorder, and Tolleration: But every man is a Law to himſelf, whoſe ſoul is grown to a perfection like that of God, and capable of Willing of Thinking, of doing nothing but what is innocent and good, what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes that ſacred place and company, what ſuits with the Majeſty of God (in whoſe immediate preſence they are) and the chaſt unſully'd purity of their own minds: And therefore to do what they pleaſe, is to do what they ought: For they can neither do nor take pleaſure in any thing but what is excellent and holy; and to theſe they have all the freedom they can wiſh.</p>
            <p>When we frail Mortals attempt any thing that is good and worthy, what rubs do we meet with? What difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties lie in our way? What checks do we feel in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures! VVhat dullneſs and irkſomneſs in our Fleſh? How
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43037:7"/>dubiouſly and cowardly we go about it, as if we were afraid to diſpleaſe our corrupt natures, or diſoblige the wicked one, by any thing that's good and vertuous! How do we reſolve, and then repent! How tremblingly do we put forth our hand, which withers in the motion, and then we recall it into our boſome! How importunately doth the fleſh preſs us to forbear! How doth Satan crowd ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe into our thoughts! How are our luſts alarm'd, and ſtand up in their own defence as if they were injuriouſly dealt with and betray'd! Thus when we would do Good, Evil is preſent with us, when we would break Priſon, and get away from theſe reſtraints, our fetters hang at our feet, we run in chains the race that is ſet before us; and are in conſtant danger to fall and be overtaken. The fleſh is a continual weight upon our Spirits, and either ſinks us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the puddle of baſe thoughts, and foul degenerous actions, or at leaſt keeps us dull and heartleſs, lazy and ſlow in our nobler undertakings aad purſuits. That as long as we car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry this load of Clay about us, we muſt expect to find it troubleſome and untoward, to every thing that is ſpiritual and ſublime. <hi>David</hi> propoſed well, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.32. <hi>I will run the way of thy Commandments,</hi> but then as if he had been ſtopt, as if the fleſh had bid him ſtand, he remembred that his Soul was under the Arreſt of the Body, and adds a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to the Promiſe, <hi>When thou ſhalt enlarge my heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not only backward it ſelf to all good motions, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbers the mind with a multitude of engagements, brings it into a neceſſary acquaintance with the VVorld, and is apt to endanger and betray it into exceſs and dotage; and how hard a thing is it to have much to do with the VVorld and be innocent! How hard to uſe it as not abuſing it! How hard to want it and not to covet it! How hard to poſſeſs it and not be endear'd to it! It is apt to cling to our thoughts and to ſtick and faſten upon our affections: It will ſtrangely grow and encroach upon us; it will inſinuate it ſelf into our very Souls, and become as great a Maſter there as God himſelf, and at length engroſs all our devoirs; for no man can ſerve God and Mammon.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:43037:8"/>
            <p>But the Bleſſed Saints have none of this Dirt upon their heels, they are not ſtak't and faſtned to the Earth, nor embodied and ſtreightn'd in theſe Tabernacles of Clay; but they are freer then Air and as active as Angels; they have no engagements to call them off from Duty, nor any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truding luſts to diſturb them at it: They have no peeviſh diſatisfi'd Paſſions to contradict what their Reaſon propoſes, nor ſuch awkard unweildy conſtitutions as we have, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract their deſigns, or ſpoil and bungle them in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Their Conſciences forbid them nothing that their wills incline to, neither are their actions bawk'd and bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Law, or impotence: But they are free to do every thing that is either their duty or delight (without regret or fear in themſelves, without gainſaying and reproof from any other, without defect and imperfection in the Act it ſelf) after the beſt and moſt accompliſh't manner.</p>
            <p>And now are we not aſham'd by this time, of what many ſenceleſs wretches among us (but Saints if you will take them in their own Language) impudently prophane theſe glorious names of light and liberty with? The carnal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the fleſh, the vitious inclinations of corrupt nature, that deſerve (and were wont to own) no better a name then Luſt, they call Light, becauſe they Pimp, and direct them through the paths of darkneſs to their ſhameful practices; ſo ſhameful that modeſty would leave them nameleſs, and yet they impudently call them Liberty: Though as St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls them, they are the very bondage of corruption the moſt fordid ſlavery in the VVorld. But they that dub their Luſts by the name of Light, and their vices by that of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, deſerve to be unnam'd, unchriſtian'd themſelves; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther profeſſion would befit them better, an <hi>Alcoran</hi> would more become them then the Bible; for there they will be match'd with a debauch't Prophet and a beaſtly Paradiſe, to their debauch't and beaſtly Religion. But the liberty of Saints is an unreſtrained power to render themſelves as Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Perfect, and (therein) as happy as glorious, as 'tis poſſible for humane nature to be.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:43037:8"/>
            <p n="4">4. Light and darkneſs are often uſed for Life and Death, ſo often that I need not inſtance: For Life and Death, and all their attendants that wait upon them and adminiſter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</p>
            <p>The Life of Saints is a life indeed, exempted both from the cauſe and ſymptoms of mortality. Sin that uſher'd Death into this World, ſhall never gain admittance into the next, the Bleſſed who have outliv'd it's poiſon, are now above it's influence, all their former ſins are pardon'd and forgotten, and their ſouls eternally ſecur'd from renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them: The poſſibility of ſinning is taken away, and all propenſions to it loſt and bury'd in the Grave. A Saint cannot think of Sin but with horrour and indignation, he cannot ſee Temptation in it, nor will the Devil himſelf have the confidence to propoſe it. Temptations were not prepared for any Life but this, where every Condition is tedious and tireſome, and poor uneaſie mortals are willing to turn every way for reſt, and to cloſe with any thing that hath but the face of pleaſure and diverſion: that the wonder is not ſo great if ſome be baited and befool'd into their own ruine. But Heaven is a place of that ſatisfaction and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, that nothing like an argument can be offer'd for a change: Nothing can be propoſed ſo tempting as what they enjoy, thoſe glories are ſo incomparably ſurpaſſing, that the ſubtle Spirit can think of nothing like them. So then Heaven hath not one hole for ſin to enter at; but it ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend into the dark Regions from whence it came, there to remain for ever. And if ſin be routed, none of its black Guard, none of its diſmal effects ſhall ſtay behind; Sorrow ſhall be a ſtranger to all. Hearts, and Tears to all Eyes, Diſeaſes and Anguiſh ſhall have no ill humors to work upon, Death ſhall have no claim to our Lives, becauſe we ſhall not ſin to forfeit them; our bodies ſhall be raiſed glorious, and immortal, fit for eternal conjunction with glorify'd Spirits, fit for the Society of Angels, and Communion with their Maker, prepared for eternity, extracted from every thing that's fading and corruptible; delicately made up in won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43037:9"/>Beauty and Splendor, to attract and entertain the Holy Love and Admiration of all that ſee them; curiouſly temper'd with exquiſite ſence, for the delicious relliſh of pure and refined pleaſures: How unconceivable then ſhall the joys of that enlightened ſtate be, when the ignobler part of man, the groſs and Elementary ſubſtance of our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, this ſordid lump of corrupt Fleſh, which here the ſoul in time grows weary of, and lays aſide as an ungrateful bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; ſhall (at the great day) riſe out of its aſhes a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Body, bedect with Light, and Glory, and Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The felicities of a glorifyed ſtate are call'd Light, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they principally conſiſt in Viſion and Knowledge. The Underſtanding is the nobleſt faculty of the Mind: And the infinite improvements, the perfect illumination, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largeing and fulfilling the capacities of it; the ſettling it in its Empire, and Government of the Soul; the ſetting it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on objects worthy of its Contemplation, the adapting thoſe objects to its Apprehenſions; or rather raiſing it's concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to ſuch infinite heights, that it may be capable of reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and fathoming the profoundeſt Myſteries; the ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning its powers, that it may be able to look upon and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the moſt Glorious luſtre's, without dazling or being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded; theſe make up (in a great meaſure) the happineſs of Souls: And therefore it is often expreſt by ſeeing of God and ſeeing of his Kingdom, and ſeeing his Glory, &amp;c. And this is the felicity of the Saints, that they ſhall have a full ſight, an open view of all that's glorious, and know all things that make for their Everlaſting Comfort and Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>But that you may the better underſtand the nature of this Beatifick Viſion, Conſider,
<list>
                  <item>1. What it is that the Saints ſhall know, And,</item>
                  <item>2. After what manner.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. What it is that the Saints ſhall know I have told you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43037:9"/>in general, that they ſhall know every thing that may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm or increaſe their Joy: And if we could tell particularly what they know, <hi>Bonum eſſet nobis,</hi> &amp;c. It were good for us to be Here; and we ſhould enjoy a Heaven as well as they. We may make a general imperfect judgement of what they know, but to give you a diſtinct account of all that comes within the vaſt comprehenſion of their inlightned Thoughts, is a work as much above a man, as the Saints are in Glory above us. And they whoſe ſouls have been taken up to the habitations of the Bleſſed, with purpoſes that they might return again, have loſt thoſe Viſions by the way, as not fit to be brought down to the notices of men, being ſo infinitely beyond the fathom of their Reaſon. St. <hi>Paul</hi> who was wrap't up to the Regions of Glory, what a broken account doth he give, of what he there ſaw and heard? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.2. &amp;c. <hi>I knew a man in Chriſt above fourteen years ago, (whether in the Body, I cannot tell; or whether out of the Body, I cannot tell: God knoweth) ſuch an one caught up to the third Heaven. And I knew ſuch a man (whether in the Body, or out of the Body, I cannot tell: God knoweth) how that he was caught up into Paradiſe, and heard unſpeakable Words, which it is not lawful or poſſible for a man to utter.</hi> No wonder he could not retain the Viſion, when he had thus loſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>John</hi> was (of all the inſpired Penmen) pickt out on purpoſe to take a view of the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to give the World a deſcription of it: Yet how imperfect is his model? How does his Relation ſavour of Earth? What groſs and Elementary materials hath he choſen to deſcribe it by; as Gold and Pearl, and pretious Stones! Into what a narrow compaſs hath he contracted the infinite dimenſions of it? The height, and length, and breadth equally twelve thouſand Furlongs, and all this to ſhape and little it to our underſtandings, to repreſent it to the eſteem of mortals in ſuch a form, ſo furniſh't and adorn'd, made up of ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials, as are moſt pretious and valuable in the Eyes of Men, and in ſuch low expreſſions as reaſon is capable of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43037:10"/>apprehending. Becauſe our ſhort ſight can diſcern but a little way, therefore this infinite World is thus repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a Map, drawn in Little, and delineated (to uſe the Apoſtles own phraſe) <hi>according to the meaſure of a Man, Rev.</hi> 21. No our underſtandings are too contracted, while they are bound up in theſe bundles of Fleſh, to conſider the amazing glory and luſtre of thoſe heavenly Manſions, that incomprehenſible Light in which the Saints for ever dwell. Yet ſomething may be gueſt at, ſomething that may raiſe our deſires, ſomething that may ſtir the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and make us Covetous and Ambitious, zealouſly concern'd to know what they know, and to partake of thoſe Bleſſed ſights, which fill their ſouls with ſo much Pleaſure and Contentment, and that we might perhaps do by theſe Three Rules.</p>
            <p>Firſt. What God hath Revealed.</p>
            <p>Secondly. What we are ignorant of.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. What wiſe men, in their beſt Thoughts, moſt deſire to know.</p>
            <p>That which God hath revealed to us concerning another Life, ſeems rather an account of what he intends we ſhall know hereafter, then a deſign that we ſhould underſtand it now. What was imperfectly ſignifi'd by the Law, was reſerved for the clearer diſcovery of the Goſpel, and to what the Goſpel hints, but comes ſhort in, Eternity ſhall reveal.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe myſteries the Goſpel treats of in a ſence above our underſtanding, our underſtanding ſhall be enlighten'd and taught to know.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Soul of man (when 'tis ſuffered to be free and ſerious) hath a natural aim at its own happineſs, and will be looking (as far as it can) into thoſe things that concern its peace, and thirſting after the knowledge of Divine matters, it cannot attain to: And it is but reaſonable to think that it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43037:10"/>ſhall be gratify'd in this Holy curioſity, otherwiſe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſuppoſe it happy. But to examine theſe general Rules no further, I ſhall venture to deſcend to ſome particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the knowledge of Saints in Light: And they are theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. They know themſelves.</item>
               <item>2. They know each other. And,</item>
               <item>3. They know God.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. They know themſelves; a knowledge that men are ſtrangely wanting in our Bodies, that we are beſt acquainted with, have many hidden parts, many unaccountable moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, many occult qualities, that neither we that bear them, nor they that ſtudy them are able to ſolve and diſcover. But for ſouls, which are the ſeat of knowledge; all we know of them is, that they are we know not what, that there is ſuch a principle working in us we experience by the effects; that it is an immortal being, it hath owned it ſelf to ſome Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers that have examin'd it, to which truth the Word of God hath given more infallible Teſtimony. But for its ſubſtance and perfection, its ſeat and reſidence, and the manner of its operations, theſe are Problems we are wont to diſcourſe, but can come to no determinate concluſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout. But the Saints are perfect in the knowledge of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; a knowledge ſo excellent that ſome Philoſophers have accounted it the greateſt wiſdom. I ſhall only inſtance in ſuch things wherein much of their felicity conſiſts, and not in that thred-bare knowledge (if there be any ſuch in Heaven) which is only curious and ſpeculative. The Saints then know,
<list>
                  <item>1. Their own Excellencies. And,</item>
                  <item>2. Their own happineſs.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. They know their own Excellencies, things that we are not onely ignorant of, but much miſtaken in: If we knew our ſelves, we ſhould value our ſelves more, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43037:11"/>have our ſelves better. We ſhould not proſtitute our ſouls to every baſe luſt, that courts and importunes us; nor ſell them at ſuch an under rate as the vanities of the world. VVe ſhould carry our ſelves more in ſtate, and ſcorn to do any thing that might misbeſeem us. We ſhould live more like men, and reaſon would ſhow it ſelf in all our actions, we ſhould purſue greater and nobler ends, ſet our thoughts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on better objects, and beſtow our Pains, and Time, and Cares to more manly purpoſes: we ſhould not bury all our thoughts in the Earth, nor make our ſouls cheap to temptation and ſin. 'Tis a fad ſign that we know not our ſelves to be Men (or elſe we know not what a man is) when we live like beaſts, when we are concern'd for our ſouls as if we had none, and ſuffer our ſelves to be govern'd and carried away by Sence, and Appetite, and Paſſion. If we knew our ſelves we ſhould give our nobleſt faculties the higheſt place in our eſteem, and poſt the reſt in their due ſubordination. We ſhould not let Reaſon be commanded by the Will, nor the Will by paſſion, nor our paſſions by the World and the Fleſh. We ſhould not make over the intereſts of our ſouls to the wanton deſires of the carnal man, as Honour, or Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or Advantage, (for what of theſe is ſo inconſiderable that a ſoul hath not been ſold for?)</p>
            <p>But the Saints know their own Excellencies, and it is their happineſs that they do ſo. What were any man the better for the richeſt treaſures in natures ſtore, if he was either ignorant that he had them, or knew not how to prize them? But they have ſouls of incomparable value and know their worth, and therefore are capable of rejoycing in their own excellencies. How do we pride our ſelves at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of our Eſtates, at the advance of Titles, which are no acceſſions to our Natures, but to our Names, or Fortunes. But what an infinite Joy will it be to them to conſider that they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, like unto the Angels in perfection, that they are right noble creatures, whoſe honour is not titular but real, not nominal but perſonal and eſſential? That they are rich in the admirable indowments of their minds
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43037:11"/>and Bodies: That they have much of the image and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God in them; nay that they are in the perfect like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Son of God, who hath taken their nature and will do it the honour to wear it eternally: That they are capable, of partaking of ſuch a happineſs as God do's, and of living like him, in a word, that they are ſuch precious beings as are worthy to be the darlings of God, the Joy of of Angels, and the Love and wonder of one another.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are not only acquainted with their Excellencies, but they rightly underſtand their own happineſs. They make no ſuch groſs miſtakes about it as we do: They do not as <hi>Solomon,</hi> and too many of the World beſide, make a multitude of experiments before they fix, and endeavour to ſettle it upon this pleaſure, or that fortune, and wear out their eternity as we do our lives, in folly and diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>But happineſs meets and embraces, and entertains them at their very entrance into heaven, from which moment their acquaintance commences and continues for ever: They know that a ſoul can be happy in nothing but the favour and fellowſhip of God, and it's own innocence and peace, and what a felicity, what a comfort ariſes from the ſence of theſe, they likewiſe know. They are not like thoſe repin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, diſcontented wretches that are in a good condition (bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then they deſerve) and yet are inſenſible of it, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful for it; but he that is leaſt in the Kingdom of God, knows ſo much happineſs in that ſtate, that he neither aſpires to be happier, nor envies thoſe that are. The ſame Light that makes happy, lets them ſee it; and as the blind eye enjoys not the comfort of the day, but is benighted at Noon, and in utter darkneſs when the Sun ſhines cleareſt; So the Glory of God (which is the Light of Heaven) would be no Joy to thoſe that live within its ſhine, if they did not ſee the illuſtrious ſplendor of it. But the Saints in Light are happy, ſo happy that they know it, and own it, and ever praiſe and glorify the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt (their bleſſed Benefactors) for it.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:43037:12"/>
            <p>Secondly, The Bleſſed in Heaven know one another.</p>
            <p>Whether perſonally or no hath been matter of diſpute; though our Saviour ſeems to have determin'd it, telling the Jews, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.28. <hi>That they ſhould ſee Abraham, and Iſaac and Jacob, and all the Prophets in the Kingdom of God,</hi> and what is there in reaſon that ſhould hinder it? Why may not <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> (once ſo nearly related) be again acquainted, and with Joy repeat the Hiſtory of the intended Sacrifice? Why may not <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> meet, and diſcourſe their old Adventures? Why may not the Bleſſed Apoſtles and Holy Martyrs be known to one another, and entertain themſelves with gladſome relations, of what they did, and what they ſuffer'd together? Why may not Friends, that lived like brethren in the Lord, that help't forward each others Salvation, whoſe ſouls were mutually dear, who were wont to pray, and adviſe, and ſerve God together, and who went to Heaven as it were hand in hand, why I ſay, may not they embrace and return each other thanks for thoſe Friendly and Chriſtian Offices? Holy <hi>David</hi> chear'd up his thoughts after the death of his Child with this Meditation, <hi>I ſhall go to him, but he ſhall not return to me,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.23. Which had been little comfort, if he had thought never to have known him more. So St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> comforted <hi>Italica</hi> an afflicted Widow, who ſadly bewail'd the loſs of her Husband; aſſuring her, <hi>That as one day ſhe ſaw him with her bodily Eyes, but diſcerned no more then his outward ſhape and Lineaments, ſo ſhe ſhould ſee him again, and in that ſight diſcern the very thoughts of his heart and be intimate to all his Counſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that's the next thing I am going to ſay, That the Saints ſhall be acquainted with each others Thoughts, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of all hearts ſhall be revealed, and every man ſhall read his Brothers ſoul. There ſhall be no ſubtile reſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no laying of heads together, no packing of thoughts, no clubbing and combining amongſt a few, to provoke the jealouſie of all the reſt; but every mans breaſt ſhall be clear and open, as free from reſerve, as it is from deſign or guile.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43037:12"/>Now none but ſuch ingenuous Minds as underſtand the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Charms of truſty Friendſhip, the Foundation whereof is laid in Vertue and Goodneſs, are able to conceive, what a wonderful raviſhment and comfort it is, for Saints thus free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſecurely to unboſome themſelves to one another, to think in common, to mingle ſouls, and to affect and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate each others joys.</p>
            <p>But Thirdly, The fundamental happineſs of the Bleſſed, the glorious Light through which they ſee and know all things, elſe is the Knowledge of God. We know him by Hear-ſay, but they by ſight, by near intimacy and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but perpetual correſpondence and familiarity; they are ever with him, and he never withdraws himſelf from their obſervation: Neither doth he appear to them vail'd and vizarded in Myſtery and Darkneſs, but his nature is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to their underſtandings: And all thoſe difficulties that ſo much puzzle and intricat our thoughts, are made eaſie and familiar. The great problem of the Trinity, the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal generation of the Son of God, and the proceſſion of the Holy Spirit, ſuch Paradoxes as reaſon can never unriddle, they are abundantly ſatisfied in. Thoſe unſoundable depths which turn the Brain and make ſome Atheiſts, and others Mad to look into, they are made infinitely happy and wiſe in the diſcovery of. They know that which it is a ſin for us to look into, and would be our ruin to diſcover: For can a man ſee God and Live? No we muſt die before we can ſee him as they do and as he is. And certainly this muſt needs be a proſpect infinitely tranſporting; Did you ever ſee any thing that pleaſed you? Did you ever conſider any thing that delighted you? Did you ever know any thing that you were glad to know? Or had you ever any rude conceptions of any good thing above your underſtanding that you deſired to know more of! Why ſum up all together, and this ſight is more than all; more then ever was in the Eye or Imagination of man enough to fulfill all our deſires, and to conſummate all our Joyes.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:43037:13"/>
            <p>The Eye ſhall be ſatisfied with ſeeing, the Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on raviſh'd with conſidering, and the unſatiable thirſt of the ſoul after Knowledge, ſhall be gratified in the higheſt and moſt unſearchable curioſities. In him we ſhall behold ſuch a ſufficiency of all things, that we ſhall deſire to know and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy no more; but ſhall ever reſt ſatisfi'd and at peace in the fruition (not of a force't and artificial contentment, but) of a plenary ſatisfaction of all our hopes and wiſhes: For we ſhall not onely ſee God, but we ſhall ſee him ours, we ſhall ſee our ſelves in the poſſeſſion and embraces of him: We ſhall foreſee a long Eternity before us, in all which we ſhall never be depriv'd of that Bleſſed Viſion, no, not for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>We ſhall ſee God, and nothing in him but what ſhall wonderfully pleaſe us: His Juſtice ſhall not ſtartle us, when we ſhall not only have eſcap't it, but ſhall be rewarded by it: His Pow'r ſholl not make us tremble, for we ſhall be no otherwiſe concern'd in it, then to conſider how happily it ſhall have brought us thither, and how infallibly it ſhall maintain and eternize our happineſs. His Omniſcience ſhall not daunt us, for we ſhall be capable of doing nothing we can be aſham'd of; but the glorious attributes of his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Mercy, of his Love and Tenderneſs, of his Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Good VVill, ſhall ever ſhine upon us in the greateſt manifeſtations. No Frown, no Anger, no Diſpleaſure ſhall ever darken or beeloud his ſerene Countenance unto us. And this it is (and more then I can tell you) to be Saints in Light; to ſee God face to face, and to ſee him as he is. <hi>For God is Light and in him is no Darkneſs at all,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Light diſcovers to the Saints not only the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, but alſo his Will with undoubted certainty and clearneſs. We ſhall not only hear his Voice, but we ſhall ſee his Thoughts, and be acquainted with all his Mind. The Divine Will ſhall be impreſt upon ours, and we ſhall know his Thoughts by our own; his deſires and ours will
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43037:13"/>look the ſame way; and it ſhall be always in our Hearts, to do that which he would have done; and to ſerve him after that manner that we ſhall be infallibly ſure to pleaſe him. Our Judgments ſhall be wholly reſign'd to his, and we ſhall approve whatſoever he does or likes of. God and his Saints have but one will, and whatſoever pleaſes God is legibly written in their own underſtanding, which muſt needs greatly contribute to their happineſs, for this keeps Heaven in perpetual peace, that there can be no debates, no differences among them; but the judgment of every ſingle member, paſſes the whole aſſembly, <hi>Nemine contradicente,</hi> and hath the Royal aſſent alſo. This ſecures the Bleſſed from all danger of doing amiſs, and from the doubts and fears of diſpleaſing: For they ſerve God after their own Wills and as they pleaſe themſelves; and what ſeems right in their own eies that is alſo acceptable unto him. This renders all their Duties eaſie and pleaſurable: Whatſoever they do is conſiſtent with their happineſs, for God requires nothing but what they are willing to; nothing but what their own thoughts are inclining to. Nay ſuch a mighty force hath the will of God upon theirs, and ſo ſtrongly are they bent unto all that is good, that they could not be happy if they did it not.</p>
            <p>That Duty and Felicity there, are the ſame thing; and the worſhip and ſervice of God their unſpeakable plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and delight.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Saints are by vertue of that Light in which they dwell, not only acquainted with the Will, but with the Providences of God alſo. I do not mean that they have an Omniſcient underſtanding of all that God do's in the world: No, this is a point that Papiſts themſelves dare not always ſtand by though a matter of great ſervice and concernment to them: But my meaning is, that there is nothing in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the affairs of Providence, that now we look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with amazement, and ſuſpition, as if they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions to the juſtice and goodneſs of God; but we ſhall
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43037:14"/>be able one day to render an account of. No Holy and Good man, that now groans under the weight of Gods Judgements and knows not why (for when he examines his life with <hi>Job,</hi> he perhaps can find no notorious inſtances of Guilt, to provoke God thus to expreſs his Vengeance and Indignation againſt him,) but when he comes to heaven he ſhall be ſtraight in the Light, and underſtand the reaſon of Gods dealing with him; and that there was infinite wiſdom and goodneſs in thoſe proceedings, then he will find that God was juſt in his diſpenſations to him, and that he ought to have no quarrel with Providence upon that account; but his ſoul will bleſs it's Maker and ſay with holy <hi>David</hi> Lord I know that in very faithfulneſs thou haſt afflicted me, and it was good for me that I was in trouble. Then all thoſe thwart and uneven Providences, that Reaſon is confounded, and that Faith ſtaggers at, ſhall entertain the contemplation of the Saints with ſingular delight. They will ſee how God hath traced the Souls of men through a thouſand turnings, and by croſſing their purpoſes endeavour'd to chaſe them from their evil haunts and cuſtoms, how his Providence hath lain upon the catch, and watch't to beguile them into the tracks of vertue and holineſs. With what holy artifice and ſtratagem he hath managed the welfare of his Church, and what variety of methods he hath taken to ſecure both her Religion and Peace: Sometimes fortifying and encouraging her by mercies and kindneſſes, and ſometimes quite the other way by Judgements and Tryals. Sometimes ſignal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing his Juſtice in the direct ruine of her Enemies, and ſometimes tolling them into a Trap and Snare by ſucceſs and triumph. How he hath made hopeful cauſes to defeat them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and bring forth contrary effects, and on the other hand brought evil out of good, and made the deſigns of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils and bad men, to ſerve the ends of his mercies and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. This is a ſweet Theme for Saints to compoſe their thankſgiving Songs upon, and to praiſe God for the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that he doth for the Children of men.</p>
            <p>Laſtly; The Saints ſhall be in the Light concerning the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43037:14"/>Judgements and Decrees of God, which are matters now of ſuch fierce diſputes among us. They ſhall fully under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the nature of the Eternal Covenant between God and Man, and the purpoſes of the Almighty in the Salvation or Condemnation of Sinners. And let the victory ſettle on which ſide it will, yet all parties of the Saints ſhall then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in one opinion; and praiſe and admire the juſtice and wiſdom and goodneſs of God in the excellent contrivance and management of that important affair; and nothing ſhall have paſt between God and us, but we ſhall be ſatisfied (howſoever we diſputed the matter in the world) that God was in the right, Let him be true and every man a Lyar.</p>
            <p>And having given you an imperfect account (as every thing we ſay of Eternity muſt needs be imperfect) of what the Saints know; I proceed to ſhew the manner how this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is convey'd into their minds, and unto what degrees of underſtanding it raiſes them, to both which I can only an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer Negatively.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Saints know immediately, they (and onely they) are above Ordinances, and need not to be thus handed to God becauſe they are always with him.</p>
            <p>They need not track the Divine footſteps, (the fartheſt way) in his Works and Providences, nor ſtudy Notions of him out of his Holy Word, nor take impreſſions from Signs and Sacraments, for they know him infinitely better from the Original, then 'tis poſſible to do from Copies and Figures. There's no Temple in the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for the Lord God Almighty, and the Lamb are the Temple of it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.22. They need neither Prayer nor Preaching, neither Offering nor Receiving: For they ſee more in the face of God then it is poſſible for theſe to teach them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They know impartially, they are ignorant of nothing that's fit or poſſible for them to know. There's no Tree in Paradiſe forbidden, but what would be the bane of them that taſt it. If God have any Reſerves of knowledge that he refuſes to make over to them, they are either ſuch as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43037:15"/>are inconſiſtent with their Happineſs, or with their Being, ſuch as would make them miſerable (as the knowledge and ſence of Evil) or ſuch as they could not be Men and know. For doubtleſs God hath left ſome ſpace, ſome degrees of perfection between us and Angels; and between them and his own nature, and theſe have their excellencies and diſtinctions that the Saints can neither arrive at, nor deſire. Now God is ſo merciful that he will not ſuffer us to know any thing that may be our ruin; and ſo juſt that we may not encroach upon the Prerogative of Angels, which would be theirs. But we ſhall be as Glorious, as Happy, as knowing in our Kind as they; and as 'tis poſſible for Men to be: And to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more then Men, would as much unman us and make us as monſtrous and deform'd, as to be ſomewhat leſs.</p>
            <p>Again 3. As the Saints ſhall be ignorant of nothing that is fit to be diſcover'd to them, ſo they ſhall erre in nothing that they ſeem to know. God is the Light by which they ſee, and he is Truth and can neither deceive them, nor will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to be miſtaken. No, he will not mock our fancies with ſcene and Pageantry, but feed our underſtandings with bleſſed Truths. He will not tempt our approaches with ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent Glory, and when we come to lay hold on it, thruſt a ſhadow into our embraces. We ſhall be where he is, and our eyes ſhall be opened that we may ſee him, and he will not ſhrink up his Beams and Brightneſs from us, to elude our knowledg; the Glaſs (the groſsneſs of our Nature) that miſrepreſented things to our underſtandings ſhall be taken, away and we ſhall know our God, and in him all the objects of our felicity as infallibly as we are known of him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We ſhall know him certainly without haeſitancy or du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, we ſhall not ſcruple and quaere as <hi>John</hi>'s Diſciples did, <hi>Art thou he, or look we for another?</hi> But we ſhall be as bold and poſitive as the convicted Apoſtle, and ſay, <hi>My Lord, and my God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus (Lord) ſhall we behold thy face in righteouſneſs, and when we awake, after thy likeneſs, we ſhall be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with it.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:43037:15"/>
            <p>And now let me prevail with you by the power of this worthy conſideration to obſerve theſe following inſtructions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That you let this glory we have been now thinking of, be always ſeated uppermoſt in your Thoughts, and let all other intereſts give place and adminiſter unto it. If you ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure this, bleſſed are you, though you ſhould be unhappy in all things elſe: This is the great end for which we came into the world; and if we fail in the accompliſhment, it had been better for us never to have been born. Methinks this ſhould be a motive of that importance, that it ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage all our Deſires, all our Studies, all our Endeavours, in the purſuit of it, That we ſhould be ſo concern'd, ſo bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi'd and taken up about it, that we ſhould have no leaſure to conſider the addreſſes of importunate Temptations, much leſs any ſtomach to be prevail'd with by them. Methinks he that hath ſuch a Heaven in his eye ſhould not look upon the World but with contempt and ſcorn, and think it a great debaſement to his reaſon, to give it any place in his thoughts and affections, that droſs and Dung ſhould ever defile that mind, that was made for the contemplation of Heaven now, and for the enjoyment of it at the next remove. How would it daunt and ſhame the wanton dalliances of the fleſh, and make it bluſh at all fond, unclean propoſals, to object againſt it the Raviſhing, but chaſt delights of the Saints in Bliſs! One ſerious thought thereof, would confront and baffle the Pleaſures and Allurements of ſence, and cauſe the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident Temptation diſgracefully to ſlink away and vaniſh. If we were but always arm'd with ſuch Meditations, with what courage ſhould we face and outbrave our preſent cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and Triumph in Affliction and Death it ſelf? With what forward reſolution and manly vigor ſhould we preſs and fight, and make our way through all difficulties; with what eagerneſs and ſpeed ſhould we run the race, if we did but ſee the Reward, the Crown, the Joy that is ſet before us?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us not endeavour to anticipate Heaven, and to be all-wiſe before our time, let us not exerciſe our thoughts
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43037:16"/>in things that are too high for us: But be contented with ſuch proportions of knowledge as God hath revealed, and enabled us to underſtand. To what purpoſe ſhould we puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zle and diſtract our ſelves and others with vain diſputes about things above us? 'Tis a dangerous thing to meddle with ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred matters we do not underſtand, we ſin in the very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, we may for ought we know commit a ſecond ſin in being miſtaken and beleiving a lie, and 'tis ſeldom ſeen but we are betrayed into a third; for ſuch diſputes ſeldom are debated, but with heat and paſſion, and end in hatred and diſſention. Let God alone with his Decrees, &amp;c. And let us mind our own duty, ſee what part we have in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, let that be our Study to know and our buſineſs to perform. As for Gods part we have no reaſon to be ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous about it, further then he hath bin pleaſed to diſcover him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. VVe may be aſſured what lies upon him, ſhall be ſaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſcharg'd, he cannot but do all things well and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and when we come to Heaven we ſhall know as much: In the mean time let us content our ſelves with theſe hopes, and have no ill thoughts of God; his Judgements are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable, but yet they are Juſt and Righteous. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us entertain no opinions of him that may impeach his Goodneſs or Equity and render them ſuſpected here, but pray that we may be of the number of thoſe Saints who ſhall ſee them brought to Light and clear'd hereafter.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Let us chearfully ſubmit to the Providences of God, though we cannot ſolve them. Let us conclude that God is juſt in his diſpenſations, though we be weak and cannot underſtand them; though we ſee not his Reaſons in the Government of the VVorld, yet we may know the defects of our own, and thereto aſcribe the cauſe, why ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral events ſeem to happen ſo prepoſterous and croſs. All things work together for good where God has to do, this ſhould eſtabliſh our confidence, and ſilence our complaints: and we ſhall ſee it though not now; this ſhould put bounds to our unreaſonable curioſity; let us but wait with Patience until our change come, and then the crooked paths ſhall be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43037:16"/>made ſtraight, and the rough places plain. Then all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts between God and us ſhall be audited and made even, and theſe Providences that appear ſo perplext and diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionate, ſhall be evidently made out both to our wonder and fatisfaction. So that a man ſhall ſay, (what a happy experience ſhall infallibly teach him) <hi>Verily, There is a Reward for the Righteous, Verily he is a God that Judgeth in the Earth.</hi> To whom be Glory, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>P. 2. <hi>l.</hi> 29. <hi>r.</hi> and that thoſe Pleaſures. <hi>l. ult. r.</hi> rational. <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>r.</hi> theſe bleſſed Souls, theſe deareſt. <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 28. <hi>r.</hi> pleaſures. <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>r.</hi> extent. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>r.</hi> conſiſts. <hi>p.</hi> 14. <hi>l.</hi> 24. for to <hi>r.</hi> ſo. <hi>p.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>r.</hi> wanting in: Our Bodies. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>r.</hi> our Souls. <hi>p.</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 34. <hi>r.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 17. <hi>l.</hi> 29. <hi>r.</hi> makes them happy. <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 12. for but perpetual. <hi>r.</hi> by perpetual.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
